JUSTIN T. VAN DIJK

E j.t.vandijk@ucl.ac.uk in linkedin.com/in/jtvandijk

W www.mappingdutchman.com **D** 0000-0001-5496-425X

Human geographer. Spatial data scientist. Lecturer. Interested in spatial inequalities and spatial justice, urban transport, and big data applications in scarce data environments. Extensive experience in the domain of Geographic Information Systems, urban studies, and transport research. Possesses a wide skill set in the field of advanced spatial analysis, experienced with Python programming, R scripting, and PostgreSQL/PostGIS.

Present Appointment

2021 – Present Lecturer, University College London

Department of Geography. Lecturer in Social and Geographic Data

Science. Contributing to the M.Sc. modules Principles of Spatial Analysis and

Data, Politics and Society as well as the undergraduate module

Geocomputation.

Previous Appointments

2020 – 2021 Associate Lecturer, University College London

Department of Geography. Associate Lecturer in Quantitative Social

Science.

2018 – 2021 **Postdoctoral Research Associate**, University College London

Department of Geography. Research Associate in the Geospatial Analytics

and Computing Research Group.

2014 – 2017 **Junior Lecturer**, Stellenbosch University

Department of Logistics. Part-time appointment.

2013 **Junior Lecturer**, Utrecht University

Department of Human Geography and Planning.

2012 **Teaching Assistant**, Stellenbosch University

Department of Logistics.

2009 – 2012 **Teaching Assistant**, Utrecht University

Department of Human Geography and Planning.

Education

2014 – 2017 **Doctor of Philosophy**, Stellenbosch University

Transport Economics. Dissertation title: "Designing Travel Behaviour Change interventions: A spatiotemporal perspective".

2011 – 2013 Master of Science, Utrecht University. GPA 4.0. Cum Laude.

Human Geography and Planning. Dissertation title: "Towards spatial justice: The spatial equity effects of a toll road in Cape Town, South Africa".

2007 – 2011 Bachelor of Science, Utrecht University. GPA 4.0.

Human Geography and Planning. Dissertation title: "Contemporary Orientalism? Representations of Islam and Muslims in the Dutch Press: a content analysis of 'De Volkskrant' and 'De Telegraaf', 2001-2010".

Journal Articles

2021

Longley, P. A., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, and Lan, T. The geography of intergenerational social mobility in Britain. *Nature Communications*. Accepted for publication.

Van Dijk, **J. T.**, Lansley, G., and Longley, P. A., Using linked consumer registers to estimate internal migration in the United Kingdom. *Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series A (Statistics in Society)*. Advance online publication. doi: 10.1111/rssa.12713

Lan, T., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, and Longley, P. A., Family names, city size distributions and residential differentiation in Great Britain, 1881-1901. *Urban Studies*. Advance online publication. doi: 10.1177/00420980211025721

2020

Van Dijk, J. T. and Longley, P. A. Interactive display of surname distributions in historic and contemporary Great Britain. *Journal of Maps* 16(1): 68-76. doi: 10.1080/17445647.2020.1746418

Kandt, J., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, and Longley, P. A. Family name origins and intergenerational demographic change in Great Britain. *Annals of the American Association of Geographers*. 110(6): 1726-1742. doi: 10.1080/24694452.2020.1717328

Engin, Z., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Lan, T., Longley, P. A., Treleaven, P., Batty, M., and Penn, A. Data-driven urban management: Mapping the landscape. *Journal of Urban Management* 9(2): 140-150. Publication. doi: 10.1016/j.jum.2019.12.001

2018

Van Dijk, J. T. Identifying activity-travel points from GPS-data with multiple moving windows. *Computers, Environment and Urban Systems* 70: 84-101. doi: 10.1016/j.compenv urbsys.2018.02.004

2017

Van Dijk, **J. T.** and Krygsman, S. C. Using GPS-based activity spaces and opportunity indicators for travel behaviour analysis. *Journal of Urban Technology* 25(2): 105-124. doi: 10.1080/10630732.2017.1400814

Van Dijk, **J. T.** and De Jong, T. Post-processing GPS tracks in reconstructing travelled routes in a GIS-environment: Network subset selection and attribute adjustment. *Annals of GIS* 23(3): 203-217. doi: 10.1080/19475683.2017.1340340

2015

Idahosa, L. O. and **Van Dijk**, **J. T.** Freedom for whom in South Africa? Inequality, unemployment and the elderly. *Development* 58(1): 96-102. doi: 10.1057/dev.2015.18

Van Dijk, **J. T.**, Krygsman, S. C., and De Jong, T. Towards spatial justice: The spatial equity effects of a toll road in Cape Town, South Africa. *Journal of Transport and Land use* 8(3): 95-114. doi: 10.5198/jtlu.2015.555

Book Chapters

2021

Van Dijk, **J. T.**, Lansley, G., and Longley, P. A., Using linked consumer and administrative data to model demographic changes in London's city fringe. In: Clarke, G., Birkin, M., and Stimson, B. (Eds.), *Applications of Big Data in Geography and Planning. An Essential Companion*, pp. 43-51. Cheltenham: Edward Elgar Publishing.

2013

Wolfensberger M., Dekker, M., **Van Dijk, J. T.**, Zubizarreta, J., Hait, C., Mann, C., and Lucas, C. Learning as salon: Honors International Collaboration. In: Mulvaney, M. K. and Klein, K. (Eds.), *Preparing Tomorrow's Global Leaders: Honors International Education*, pp. 75-84. Lincoln: National Collegiate Honors Council. NCHC Monograph Series.

Conference Proceedings

2021

Van Dijk, J. T. and Longley, P. A. Developing a data infrastructure for bespoke demographic analysis. *Proceedings of the 29th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK)*. Cardiff: Cardiff University. doi: 10.5281/zenodo.4664749

Chen, M., Chi, B., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, and Longley, P. A. The use of Linked Consumer Registers to understand social mobility and residential mobility. *Proceedings of the 29th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK*). Cardiff: Cardiff University. doi: 10.5281/zenodo.4665856

Kuleszo, J., Coulter, R., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, and Longley, P. A. Linking consumer datasets to chart residential moves in private rental housing in England and Wales. *Proceedings of the 29th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK)*. Cardiff: Cardiff University. doi: 10.5281/zenodo.4665818

Van Dijk, J. T. and Longley, P. A. Platial geo-temporal demographics using family names. In: Westerholt, R. and Mocnick, F.-B. (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 2nd International Symposium on Platial Information science (PLATIAL'19)*.

Warwick: Warwick University. 23-31. doi: 10.5281/zenodo.3628863

Van Dijk, J. T., Lansley, G., Lan, T., and Longley, P. A. Using the spatial analysis of family names to gain insight into demographic change. *Proceedings of the 27th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK)*. Newcastle: Newcastle University.

Lan, T., Lansley, G., **Van Dijk, J. T.**, and Longley, P. A. Geocoding historical census records in England and Wales. *Proceedings of the 27th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK)*. Newcastle: Newcastle University.

Van Dijk, J. T. and Krygsman, S. C. Mobile technologies for data collection in sub-Saharan Africa: An outlook to the future of mobility research. #CelebrateGeography: Proceedings of the 11th Biennial Conference of the Society of South African Geographers (SSAG 2016). Stellenbosch: SunMedia. 180-189.

Van Dijk, J. T. and Krygsman, S. C. Gathering individual travel data with GPS-enabled smartphones: A proof of concept study. *Proceedings of the 34th Southern African Transport Conference (SATC 2015). Pretoria: Southern Africa Transport Conference*. 448-460.

Professional Publications

Van Dijk, J. T. and De Jong, T. Medische voorzieningen in kaart.

Bereikbaarheid medische voorzieningen in Bushbuckridge, Maruleng en
Sekhukhune [Accessibility of Medical services in Bushbuckridge, Maruleng
and Sekhukhune]. Geografie 19 (5): 18-20.

Authored Books

Van Dijk, J. T. Designing Travel Behaviour Change Interventions: a spatiotemporal perspective [Ph.D. dissertation]. Stellenbosch:
 Stellenbosch University. Persistent URL: https://doi.org/10.11/102809

Research and Travel Grants

Co-funded and Collaborative ESRC Ph.D. Studentship, UBEL DTP £ 57,761 / 3 years (co-l, with P. A. Longley)
 Frank Carter Travel Fund, University College London £ 550
 Postgraduate travel grant, National Research Foundation South Africa ZAR 24,222

2015 NRF-DST innovation scholarship, National Research Foundation and

Department of Science and Technology South Africa

ZAR 330,000 / 3 years

Stellenbosch merit bursary, Stellenbosch University

ZAR 50,000 / 2 years

2014 Scholarship award for full-time doctoral studies, Stellenbosch University

ZAR 390,000 / 3 years

Created Research Datasets

2021 Migration Model, 1997 – 2020

The Migration Model is a dataset that ascribes records pertaining to individuals that vacate a property to their most probable destination address, using a UK-wide population data set: the Linked Consumer Registers. The dataset comprises circa 42 million records. Access to this dataset can be secured through the Consumer Data Research Centre (data.cdrc.ac.uk).

2021 Linked Consumer Registers, 1997 – 2020

The Linked Consumer Registers are a dataset that contain the names and addresses for adults in the UK in annual snapshots from 1997 onwards to 2020. They are compiled from reported outputs from linking public versions of the electoral roll and consumer registers (supplied by value-added resellers). The dataset comprises circa 141 million records. Access to this dataset can be secured through the Consumer Data Research Centre (data.cdrc.ac.uk).

Teaching Experience

2021 – Present Lecturing, University College London

- GEOG0114: Principles of Spatial Analysis (M.Sc.). Module page: <u>itvandijk.github.io/GEOG0114/</u>

- GEOG0163: Data, Politics and Society (M.Sc.). *Module convenor*.

Module page: <u>itvandijk.github.io/GEOG0163/</u>

- GEOG0030: Geocomputation (B.Sc.). Module convenor.

Module page: jtvandijk.github.io/POLS0008/

- Principal dissertation supervisor of two B.Sc. students

- Principal dissertation supervisor of four M.Sc. students

2020 – 2021 **Lecturing**, University College London

- GEOG0114: Principles of Spatial Analysis (M.Sc.). Module page: <u>itvandijk.github.io/GEOG0114_20202021/</u>

- GEOG0125: Advanced Topics in Social and Geographic Data Science (M.Sc.). Module page: itvandijk.github.io/GEOG0125_20202021/

- POLS0008: Introduction to Quantitative Research Methods (B.Sc.). Module page: jtysu.github.io/POLS0008-20202021/

- Principal dissertation supervisor of two M.Sc. students

2019 – Present **High-school Student Supervision,** Nuffield Foundation

Supervision of first-generation prospective university students as part of the annual Nuffield Future Researchers widening participation programme

2019 Seminar Speaker, University College London

Co-organiser and speaker in the "Technical Tuesdays" Seminar Series on methods and techniques for quantitative researchers. Module material: github.com/jtvandijk/TechnicalTuesdays

2014 – 2017 **Lecturing**, Stellenbosch University

- Spatial Accessibility and Transport Network Analysis (B.Sc. Hons, M.Sc.)

- Secondary dissertation supervisor of two B.Sc. Hons students

2013 **Lecturing**, Utrecht University

- Introduction to Human Geography and Planning (B.Sc.)

- Research Methods and Techniques (B.Sc.)

- Introduction to Geographic Information Systems (B.Sc.)

- Advanced Geographic Information Systems (B.Sc., M.Sc.)

- Principal dissertation supervisor of three B.Sc. students

2012 **Teaching Assistant**, Stellenbosch University

- Spatial Accessibility and Transport Network Analysis (B.Sc. Hons, M.Sc.)

2009 - 2012 **Teaching Assistant**, Utrecht University

- Introduction to Geographic Information Systems (B.Sc.)

- Advanced Geographic Information Systems (B.Sc., M.Sc.)

- Transport Geography (B.Sc.)

- Honours College Geosciences (B.Sc.)

Ph.D. supervision

2021 - Present Secondary Supervisor, University College London

Shunya Kimura on the topic of "Geographies of harmful gambling behaviour and their remediation".

Ph.D. examination

2020 **Ph.D. upgrade**, University College London

Jakub Wyszomierski on the topic of "Hybrid geodemographics and creation of the 2021 Output Area Classification"

Invited talks and Conference Presentations

2021	"New data on equality, exclusion and social change in London and the UK". Levelling Up and London, London Research and Policy Partnership <i>London, United Kingdom, September 17, 2021</i> .
2021	"Developing a data infrastructure for bespoke demographic analysis". 29th Conference of GIS Research UK. <i>Cardiff, United Kingdom, September 14 – September 16, 2021.</i>
2020	"Applied Geoinformatics: Insights into human mobility patterns". Guest lecture Department of Physical Planning [online]. School of Architecture and Planning New Delhi, India, October 29, 2020.
2019	"Platial geo-temporal demographics using family names". 2nd International Symposium on Platial Information science. <i>Coventry, United Kingdom, September 5 – September 6, 2019.</i>
	"Using the spatial analysis of family names to gain insight into demographic change". 27th Conference of GIS Research UK. <i>Newcastle, United Kingdom, April 23 – April 26, 2019.</i>
2017	"Using GPS-enabled smartphones for Voluntary Travel Behaviour Change interventions". Guest lecture Utrecht University Summer School on "GPS data analysis". <i>Utrecht University, the Netherlands, July 12, 2017.</i>
2016	"Mobile data collection techniques in sub-Saharan Africa: An outlook to the future of transport research". 11th Biennial Conference of the Society of South African Geographers. Stellenbosch, South Africa, September 25 – September 25, 2016.
	"Designing a Voluntary Travel Behaviour Change Intervention: Smartphones and Space-Time Accessibility Analysis". Mobile Tartu 2016. Tartu, Estonia, June 29 – July 1, 2016.
	"GPS data analysis". Guest lecture Utrecht University in the module "Introduction to GIS". <i>Utrecht University, the Netherlands, February 18, 2016.</i>
2015	"GPS data analysis". Guest lecture Utrecht University in the module "Introduction to GIS". <i>Utrecht University, the Netherlands, November 25, 2015.</i>
	"Gathering individual travel data with GPS-enabled smartphones: A proof of concept study". 34th Southern African Transport Conference. <i>Pretoria, South Africa, 6 July – July 9, 2015.</i>
2014	"Twenty years of Freedom: The role of the Old Persons Grant in addressing unemployment and inequality in a young democracy". 12th Development Dialogue "Rethinking Democracy". The Hague, the Netherlands, October 16 – October 17, 2014.

"Towards spatial justice: The spatial Equity Effects of a Toll Road in Cape Town, South Africa". World Symposium on Transport and Land Use. *Delft, the Netherlands, June 24 – June 27, 2014.*

Professional Societies

2021 – Present Fellow of the Royal Geographical Society (with Institute of British Geographers)

Community Service and Engagement

2021 Consumer Data Insights for Housing Policy Workshop

Presentation and participation in stakeholder workshop to showcase work on housing and residential mobility. *London, United Kingdom, June 26, 2021.*

2020 – Present Under One Sky

Volunteering. Provision of food and assistance to the homeless community

living on the streets of London.

2014 – 2015 Social Sciences for Development conference

Member of the local organising committee at Stellenbosch University for

the 2015 Social Sciences for Development conference.

Web Development

2019 – 2021 Gamble Aware

Data analysis, web mapping, and visualisation of the geographical distribution of supply and demand for treatment and support for problematic gamblers. Latest maps are available through:

www.begambleaware.org/gambleaware-gb-maps

2018 - Present GBNames

GBNames explores the spread of family names across Great Britain, using historic censuses and recent consumer registers, and links surnames to

consumer data statistics. Website available through:

apps.cdrc.ac.uk/gbnames/

External Projects

2021 World Bank

Generation of travel time indicators and market access indicators for small administrative units in Ethiopia. This project is part of a wider study conducted by the World Bank that aims to identify and tackle deeply rooted binding constraints that could hamper the gains of economic growth being spread evenly across regions and between rural and urban

areas.

2020 UCL, Bloomsbury and East London Doctoral Training Partnership

Scoping study, consisting of both desk research and in-person interviews, to identify potential factors and themes that underpin successful partnerships and collaborations between academia and industry.

2019 Greater London Authority

Preparation of selected data products on ethnicity, population churn, migration, and social mobility for the Greater London Authority.

2016 – 2017 Harambee Youth Employment Accelerator

Data analysis using well-known statistical techniques as well as more advanced machine learning classifiers for Harambee Youth Employment Accelerator to better understand, and possibly predict, successful job

placements.

2009 AfriScope

Contributions to a study on the accessibility of government services in the Integrated Sustainable Rural Development (ISRD) Nodes in South Africa.

Review

2021 Transactions in GIS

Environment and Planning B: Urban Analytics and City Science

2020 Computers, Environment, and Urban Systems

Journal of Transport Geography

Transactions in GIS

2019 Transactions in GIS

Journal of Transport Geography

The Israel Science Foundation (Grant review)
Journal of Traffic and Transportation Engineering

2018 Journal of Transport Geography

Computers, Environment, and Urban Systems

2016 Area Development and Policy2015 Journal of Transport and Land Use

Core Technical Skills

Geographic Information Systems R, Python, Q-GIS, ESRI suite

Data processing R, Python, Unix shell, GNU Parallel

Data analysisR, PythonData visualisationggplot2Project managementGit, GitHubWeb mappingLeaflet.js

Web development HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Django

Database management PostgreSQL, PostGIS

Typesetting LaTeX, markdown, rmarkdown, bookdown

Language Proficiency

Dutch Native proficiency

English Full professional proficiency isiXhosa Basic conversational proficiency

References

Professor Paul Longley - Professor of Geographic Information Science, University College London

E p.longley@ucl.ac.uk **T** +44 20 7679 0500

Dr Jens Kandt - Associate Professor Urban Geography and Data Science, Centre for Advanced Spatial Analysis

E j.kandt@ucl.ac.uk **T** +44 20 3108 3880

Dr Neil Rankin - Chief Executive Officer, Predictive Insights; Extraordinary Associate Professor Economics, Stellenbosch University

E neil@predictiveinsights.net **T** +27 83 296 0907